Stanford
University often asked question what's
the difference between bio 150 bio 250
and is it humbio
160 no difference it's exactly the same
so like the same requirements same units
so take whichever one makes your life
easiest let's see any other procedural
stuff well the answer are back from
Monday's
questionnaire and a uh variety of
interesting answers not surprisingly
given the size of a group why have you
taken this course uh really want to know
about animal behavior but willing to
deal with
humans uh because I'm substituting it
for Bio 43 which I don't want to
take my dad used to make me read books
about human behavior in biology is
punishment that doesn't make any sense I
know one of the TA so I figure that
guarantees me an
A okay guys it's in New York Court uh
one I really liked because I want to be
a filmmaker after college yay
interdisciplinary um what else my first
grade teacher is making me Tom mcfaden
told me
to I'm a hyper oxygenated diletant um I
wanted to somewhat correctly pointing
out why have you taken this class I
haven't taken it yet a number of people
reporting that in fact that was the
correct answer and my favorite why have
you taken this course
yes
okay relevant background relevant
background I'm human I'm human and I
often behave I'm human and I have
biology uh 19 years of being confused
about human behavior uh not really sort
of uh seeing crazy behavior as an RA and
an all Frost dorm and I date a
biologist let's see there was also the
question on there of did the thing on
the board look more like an A or a b and
just to really facilitate that one I
forgot to put the A and the B up um but
that Taps into a cognitive something or
other which maybe I'll get back to at
some point telephone numbers reading
them off accuracy dramatically tanked as
soon as the three number four number
Motif went down the tubes and when it
came back briefly accuracy came back a
little bit
finally uh let's see all of you guys
conform to a standard frequent gender
difference which is everybody was
roughly equally by gender roughly
equally likely to see dependent as the
opposite of independent a small minority
went for inter
interdependent um however one finding
that has come up over and over is that
far more females are interested in peace
than males males are more interested in
Justice okay have you taken the bio core
quote no way Jose uh somebody pointing
out quite correctly don't settle for
peace or Justice then of course there
was the person who responded to that
question by writing those words are just
symbols need to know assumed
meeting
okay uh there was one questioner that
was carefully signed and something
approaching calligraphy it was so
beautiful and was otherwise blind
uh for years running the course the uh
subject that most people really want to
hear and most people really don't want
to hear is about the biology of
religiosity and for 22 years running now
Stanford students are more interested in
depression than sex okay so we start off
I keep telling Hennessy about this but
nothing gets done okay we start off we
start off if I can open this
which is something you could do if you
have a certain type of training if
you're some osteologist or whatever
these folks are called if you are
presented those two skulls and told this
one's a female this one's a male you can
begin to figure out stuff like how heavy
how large the body was of that
individual what diseases they had had
they undergone malnutrition had they
given birth a lot of times a few times
were they bipedal all sorts of stuff you
could figure out from just looking at
these skulls what today's lecture and
Friday's is about is the fact that with
the right tools under your belt you
could look at these two skulls and know
that information you're a field
biologist and you've discovered this
brand new species and you see that this
one nurses an infant shortly before
leaping out of the tree leaving only the
skull and this one has a penis shortly
before leaving leaping out of the tree
and leaving leaving a skull so all you
know is this is an adult female and
adult male and if you've got the right
tools there you can figure out who's
more likely to cheat on the other is the
female more likely to mess around or is
the male how high are the levels of
aggression does the female tend to have
twins or one kid at a time do females
choose males because they have good
parenting skills or because they're big
hunky guys what levels of differences in
life expectancy do they live the same
length of time you would be able to tell
whether they have the same life
expectancy or if there's a big
discrepancy between the two all sorts of
stuff like that merely by applying a
certain piece of logic that dominates
all of this okay so you're back reading
those time life nature books back when
and there was always a style of thing
you would go through which is they
describe some species doing something
absolutely Ely amazing and unlikely and
it go like this the giraffe the giraffe
has a long neck and it obviously has to
have a big heart to pump all that blood
up there and you lock up a whole bunch
of biomechanics people with you know
slide rules and out they come out with
this prediction as to how big the
giraffe heart should be and how thick
the walls and you go and you measure a
giraffe heart and it's exactly what the
equations predicted and you say isn't
nature amazing or you read about some
like desert rodents that drink once
every three months and another bunch of
folks have done math and figured out
like how many miles long the renal
tubules have to be and somebody goes and
studies it and it's exactly as you
expect it isn't nature wonderful no
nature isn't wonderful you couldn't have
giraffes unless they had hearts that
were that big you couldn't have rodents
living in the desert unless they had
kidneys that worked in a certain way
there is an inevitable logic about how
organisms function how organisms are
built how organisms have evolved solving
this problem of optimizing a solution
and what the next two lectures are about
is you can take the same exact
principles and apply them to thinking
about the evolution of behavior the same
sort of logic where just as you could
sit there and with logical principles
come to the point of saying a giraffe's
heart is going to be this big you can go
through a different realm of logic built
around evolutionary principles and
figure out all sorts of
aspects of social behavior and we
already know what's involved in say
optimizing what's the optimal number of
whatever is in your kidney what's the
optimal Behavior strategy or something
all of us as soon as we got like some
kid sibling learned how to do the
optimal strategy and Tic-tac-toe and so
that you could never lose and it's
totally boring but that's a case of
figuring out the optimal solution to
behavior reaching what is called the
Nash equilibrium and actually I have no
idea what I just said but I like making
reference to Nash because it makes me
feel quantitative or something so that
is called the Nash equilibrium the Nash
equilibrium and what the entire Point
here is the same sort of process of
figuring out what are the rules of
optimizing Tic Tac Toe Behavior can be
built upon the principles Evolution to
figure out all sorts of realms of
optimized social behavior and broadly
this is a field that's known as
sociobiology emerging in the late 1970s
mid 1970s or so and by the late 1980s
giving birth to another discipline known
as evolutionary psychology the notion
that you cannot understand behavior and
you cannot understand internal
psychological States outside the context
of evolution had something to do with
sculpting those behaviors and those
those psyches so to start off with that
basic song and dance about Darwin just
to make sure we're up to speed on this
Darwin just to get some things out of
the way Darwin did not discover
Evolution people knew about Evolution
long before that Darwin came up with the
notion of a mechanism for evolution
natural selection and in fact Darwin is
the inventor of that there was another
guy Alfred Russell Wallace the two of
them and for some reason Wallace has
gotten screwed historically and Darwin
gets much more attention but starting
off with a darwinian view of how
Evolution works first thing being that
there is evolution traits in populations
change over time traits can change
enough that in fact you will get
speciation new species will form and the
logic of darwinian evolution is built on
just a few couple of very reasonable
steps first one is that there are traits
that are heritable
traits that could be passed on one
generation to the next traits that we
now can translate in our modern
paraments into traits that are genetic
and we will see soon how that's totally
not correct to have said that but traits
that are
heritable the next thing is that there
is variability among those traits
there's different ways in which this
trait can occur and they're all
heritable the next critical thing some
versions of those traits are more
adaptive than others some versions work
better for you for example giraffe who
wind up with hearts the size of like a
tomato that's not an optimal version
amid the range of variability some will
carry with them more Fitness more
adaptiveness than others and that
translates into another sound bite
that's got to be gotten rid of all of
this is not about survival of the most
adapted it's about reproduction of
something we will come to over and over
again it's about the number of copies of
genes you leave in the next Generation
so you've got to have traits that are
heritable there's got to be variability
in them some of those traits are more
adaptive than others some of those
traits make it more likely that that
organism passes on copies of its genes
into the Next Generation and throw those
three pieces together and what you will
get is evolution in populations changing
frequencies of traits and when you throw
in one additional piece which is every
now and then the possibility to have a
random introduction of a new type of
trait in there modern parland a mutation
from that you could begin to get actual
large changes in what a population looks
like okay so these are the basic
building blocks of Darwin and it is easy
to apply to giraffe's hearts and kidneys
of Desert Rats and everything we think
about in the world of physiology Anatomy
in the context of evolution so how do
you apply it to behavior and the basic
notion for folks who want to come from
this Darwin in Tradition into thinking
about behavior is you do the exact same
thing there are behaviors that are
heritable types traits classes of
behaviors they come with a certain
degree of variation among individuals
some versions of them are more adaptive
than others over time the more adaptive
versions will become more commonplace
and every now and then you can have
mutations that introduce new variability
totally logical absolutely unassailable
and what we're going to spend an insane
amount of time in this class on is one
simple assumption in there which is that
certain behaviors are heritable that
certain behaviors have genetic
components and as you'll see this one is
just going to run through every lecture
wrestling with that issue there this is
a big incendiary issue there as to how
genetic and that's not the same thing as
saying how genetically determined how
genetic behavior is okay so that's going
to be a issue we come back to again and
again so now transitioning into how you
would apply these darwinian principles
first thing before starting a caveat
you're going to wind up in order to
think about all of this most efficiently
hopefully do some personifying
personifying as in you'll sit around and
saying well what would a female
chimpanzee want to do at this point to
optimize the number of copies of her
jees in the Next Generation what would
this brine shrimp want to do to deal
with this environmental stressor what
would this you know cherry tree do
they're not planning they are not
conscious they're not taking classes in
evolutionary biology what would this
organism want to do is just a shorthand
for something sculpted by the sort of
exigencies of evolution and producing
the optimal they wanted do this this is
just going to be a shorthand throughout
once you get past the Apes nobody is
wanting to do any of these optimization
things so just getting that sort of
terminology out of the way okay so we
start off with what's the first building
block of applying darwinian principles
to behavior something that is absolutely
critical to emphasize because the first
thing we all need to do is unlearn
something we all learned back when on
all those National Geographic specials
and that would consist instantly teach
us something about this aspect of
evolution and would always teach it to
us wrong here's the scenario so you're
watching and there's this Wildlife
documentary it's it's Dawn on the
Savannah and you see there's a whole
bunch of lions on top of some big old
dead thing some Buffalo or something and
they're chewing away and having a fine
time so something happens at that point
which is they have to deal with how they
divvy up the food or let me give you
another example another standard sort of
endless vignette that comes up in these
films once again now you're back on the
Savannah it's not dawn this time but you
are looking at one of the Magnificent
things of the natural world which is the
migration of zebras throughout East
Africa a herd of two million of them
migrate around following a cyclical
pattern of rains so they're always going
where the grass is greener so you've got
this wonderful herd of 2 million
wilderbeast and there's a problem which
is there's some great field right in
front of them full of grass and bummer
there's a river in between them in the
next field and especially a bummer a
river teaming with crocodiles just ready
to grab them so what are the wilderbeast
going to do and according to the
National Geographic type specials we
would get out would come a solution
there's all the wilderbeast hemming and
ha in this agitated state by the end
edge of the river and suddenly from the
back of the crowd comes this elderly
wilderbeast who pushes his way up to the
front stands on the edge of the river
and says I sacrifice myself for you mind
Kinder and throws himself into the river
where immediately the Crocs get busy
eating him up and the other two million
wilderbeast could tiptoe around the
other way across the river and
everybody's fine and you're then saying
why' this guy do this why did this guy
fling himself into the river and we
would always get the answer at that
point the answer that is permeated as
like the worst Urban myth of evolution
whatever why did he do that because
animals behave for the good of the
species this is the notion that has to
be completely trashed right now animals
behaving for the good of the species
really came to the Forefront a guy in
the early 60s named win Edwards
hyphenated win Edwards some hyphenated
Brit zoologist Who pushed most strongly
this notion of of that animals behave
for the you know good of the species he
is reviled throughout every textbook wi
Edwards and group selection that would
be the term selection for the good of
groups for the selection for the good of
the species win Edward and group
selection I'm sure the GU did all sorts
of other useful things and anyone who
really is has any depth to them would
find out but all I know is that the guy
is the one who came up with group
selection animals behave for the good of
the species
this isn't the case at all animals
behave for passing on as many copies of
their genes as possible and what we'll
see is when you start looking at the
nuances of that sometimes it may look
like behaving for the good of the
species but it really isn't the case so
animals behave in order to maximize the
number of copies of genes they leave in
the next Generation remember not surviv
with the fittest reproduction to the
fittest so first thing you need to to do
is go back to that vignette and saying
uh so what's up with the wilderbeast
there and what's up with the elderly guy
who jumps in the river and finally when
you look at them long enough instead of
the camera crew showing up for 3 minutes
when you study this closely enough you
see something that wasn't Apparent at
first which is this elderly wilderbeast
is not fighting his way through the
crowd this guy is being pushed from
behind this guy is being pushed from
behind because all the other ones are
saying yeah yeah get the old guy on The
River sacrificing himself my ass this
guy is getting pushed in by everybody
else he is not sacrificing himself for
the good of the species he does not like
the idea of this whatsoever so he gets
pushed in because the old weak guy none
of this group selection stuff what came
in by the 70s as a replacement a way to
think about this is this notion of
animals including us behaving not for
the good of the species of the group but
to maximize number of copies of genes
left in the Next Generation and what you
see is three ways in which this could
occur three building blocks the first
one being known as individual selection
the first one built around the notion
that sometimes the behavior of an animal
is meant to optimize the number of
copies of its genes that it leaves in
the Next Generation by itself
reproducing the drive to reproduce the
drive to leave more copies of one's
genes this was one summarized really sort
of tersely as sometimes a chicken is an
egg's way of making another
chicken. No, that's backwards.
Sometimes a chicken is an egg's way of
making another egg. Okay, ignore that
sometimes what the guy said is sometimes
a chicken is an egg's way of making
another egg. All this behavior stuff and
all this animate sort of social
interaction is just an epiphenomenon to
get more copies of the genes into the
next generation. Individual selection a
subset of way of thinking about this is
selfish genes what behavior is about is
maximizing number of copies of genes in
the next generation and sometimes the
best way to do it sometimes the way that
animals maximize is to get as many
copies by way of reproducing themselves.
It's not quite equivalent to a selfish
gene but for our purposes individual
selection.
and this can play out in a number of
Realms and bringing in sort of a big
dichotomy and thinking about
evolutionary pressures Darwin and the
theory of natural selection what natural
selection is about is processes bringing
about an organism who is more adaptive
what we just went through. Darwin soon
recognized there was a second realm of
selection which he called sexual
selection and what that one's about is
this is selecting for traits that have
no value whatsoever ever in terms of
survival or anything like that traits
that carry no adaptive value but for
some random, bizarro reason the opposite
sex likes folks who look this way so
they get to leave more copies of their
genes and suddenly you could have
natural selection bringing about big
sharp antlers and male moose and they
use that for fighting off Predators or
fighting with the male that would be
natural selection sexual selection might
account for the fact that like the
antlers or green paisley patterns all
over for that and for some reason that
looks cool to female moose mooses and
what you wind up getting as a mechanism
for sexual selection is as long as
individuals prefer to mate with
individuals with some completely
arbitrary traits those traits will also
become more common so this dichotomy of
natural selection for traits driven by
traits that really do Aid leaving copies
of genes outside the realm of just sheer
sexual preference sexual selection and
sometimes they can go in absolutely
opposite directions you can get some
species where the female fish prefer
male fish that have very bright
coloration and that's advantageous then
to have the bright coloration by means
of sexual selection but the bright
coloration makes you more likely to get
predated by some other fish natural
selection pushing against bright
coloration in males very often often
you've got the two going against each
other having to balance so how would
that be applied in this realm of
individual selection this first building
block sometimes an egg damn sometimes a
chicken is an egg's way of making
another egg sometimes what behavior is
about is one individual trying to
maximize the number of copies of their
genes in the Next Generation a natural
selection manifestation of it being
you're good at running away from
predators selection for speed for
certain types of muscle metabolism for
certain sensory systems that will tell
you there's somebody scary around that
would be the realm of that. Individual
selection selecting in the realm of
sexual selection to have more of
whatever those traits are that are
attractive so this first building block
it's not group selection it's not
behaving for the good of the species
it's behaving to maximize the number of
copies of one's genes in the Next
Generation and the most straightforward
way is to behave in a way to maximize
the number of times you reproduce
yourself second building block which is
there's another way of accomplishing the
same thing that you just did with
individual selection as follows one of
the things that could be relied upon in
life is that you are related to your
relatives and what you get is the more
closely related you are the more genes
you share in common with them on a
statistical level identical twins share
100% of their genes full siblings 50%
half siblings 25% this is exactly
something that's going to be covered in
the catchup section this week if you're
not comfortable with this stuff, this
sort of thing will be reviewed in more
detail okay so the closer a relative is
to you the more copies... the more
genes they share in common with you. So
suddenly you've got this issue you're an
identical twin and your identical
sibling has the same genes that you do
individual selection you will be just as
successful as passing on copies of
your genes into the next generation if
you forego reproducing to make it
possible for your identical twin to do
so because on a level of just sheer
numbers of copies of genes in the Next
Generation they are equivalent and
sometimes you will thus get behavior
which really decreases the reproductive
success of an individual in order to
enhance the success of a
relative but you've got a constraint
there which is all of your relatives
don't share all your genes with you they
have differing degrees of relatedness
and what that winds up producing is
another Factor another observation one
of the great like witty geneticists of
all time a guy named haldane who
apparently once in a bar was trying to
explain this principle to somebody and
came up and said I will gladly lay down
my life for two brothers or eight
cousins and that's the math of the
relatedness you passing on one copy of
your genes to the next generation is
from the sheer mathematics of just how
evolution is going to play out over the
generations is exactly equivalent as
giving up your life for eight cousins to
be able to each pass on a copy of their
genes because you share 1/8 with each of
them and it winds up being a whole or
and it's that math and out of that you
get something that makes perfect sense
instantly which is evolution selects for
organ isms cooperating with their
relatives something along those lines
and thus we have the second building
block known as kin selection Inclusive
fitness kin selection first building
block individual selection passing on
copies of your own genes as a way to
maximize future success second version
helping out relatives helping out
relatives in terms of increasing their
reproductive success with this vicious
mathematical logic which is you know one
identical twin two half SI two full
siblings eight cousins and so on as a
function of degree of relatedness and
what this begins to explain is a whole
world in animal behavior of animals
being obsessed with kinship animals
being fully aware of who is related to
who and what sorts of ways animals being
utterly aware of you cooperate with
relatives but as a function of how
closely related they are animals put us
in social anthropology and kinship terms
and could you marry the daughter of your
uncle's third wife or whatever to shame
in terms of how much a lot of social
animals deal with relatedness. So,
Inclusive fitness kin selection here
would be evidence for it here's one
example very cool study done some years
back by a couple sa farth and Cheney
University of Pennsylvania looking at
vervet monkeys and these were vervet
monkeys out in Tanzania I believe and
what they did was a whole bunch of these
vervent monkeys were sitting around and
they the researchers had made really
high quality record recordings of
various vocalizations from the monkeys
over time so they had the sound of each
animal giving an alarm call giving a
friendly gesture call giving a whatever
and what they would then do is hide a
microphone inside some bushes and play
the sound of one of the infants from the
group giving an alarm call
so what does the mother of that infant
do she instantly gets agitated and looks
over at the bush that's her child all of
that how to know that everyone else in
that verid group understands kin
selection what does everybody else do
they all look at the
mother that's whoever's mother what is
she going to do next they understand the
relatedness and they understand what the
response will be all the other vervets
look at the mother at that point Point
whoa I'm sure glad that's not my kid
giving an alarm call from the bushes
they understand kinship another version
of that that came out in these studies
so you've got two females each of whom
has a kid a daughter or whatever and
female a and female B and one day female
A does something absolutely rotten to
female B and later that day the child of
female B is more likely than chance to
do something rotten to the child of
female A.
they keeping track of not only Revenge
but not revenge on the individual who
did something miserable to you but
displaced by one degree of reproduction
keeping track of kinship. Animals can do
this all sorts of primate species can do
this and as we'll see all sorts of other
species can do this also there's that
caveat again all sorts of other species
want to figure out who their cousins
they don't want to figure out... Evolution
has sculpted an ability to optimize
behavior along lines of relatedness in
all sorts of species. So how would
natural selection play out in this realm
of kin selection I will lay down my life
for eight cousins. And that's just sort
of obvious there by now how would sexual
selection play out in this realm? I am
willing to expend great amounts of
energy to convince people that my
sibling is incredibly hot. And with any
chance, then passing on more copies of
genes that would be inclusive fitness
kin selection in both cases decreasing
your own reproductive potential by way
of being killed by a predator to save
the eight cousins or having to spend so
much time haranguing about your sibling.
Doing that in order to increase the
reproductive success of relatives where
you were willing to give up more energy
and potential on your part the more
closely related the individual is. So you
throw those two pieces together and
you're suddenly off and running with
explaining a lot of animal behavior.
Individual selection none of this for
the good of the species maximizing the
number of copies of your own genes and
the easiest way, the most straightforward
is you yourself maximizing
reproduction. Foundation number two to
the whole thing kin selection. Sometimes
the best way of leaving more copies and
genes in the next generation is using up
your own reproductive potential for
going to help relatives as a function of
degree of
relatedness. Okay that's great so now the
third piece the third final building
block of making sense of social behavior
in the context of real contemporary
evolutionary theory the third block here
which is you look at animals and they're
not all just competing with
non-relatives and things animals like
forgo competition at certain points
animals would have the potential to be
aggressive to other other animals and
they will forgo doing so and there's one
circumstance in which that can happen
where you get what is called a rock
paper scissor scenario you've got
animals A, B, and C a has a means of
damaging B but it costs a B has a means
of damaging C but it costs b c can
damage a but it costs a and you get the
right distribution of individuals with
one of those traits in a population and
you will reach a rock scissors paper
equilibrium where nobody is doing
anything rotten to each other great
example totally cool example that got
published some Years Ago by a guy named
Brendan Bohanan who was assistant
professor in the department here at the
time he was studying something or other
about bacteria showing a rock paper
scissor circumstance you had three
different types three different versions
of this bacteria in this Colony he had
made the first one could generate a
poison but it cost it had to put the
effort into making that poison and
protecting itself from that poison all
of that the second type was vulnerable
to the poison it happened to have some
transporter on its membrane that took up
the poison and that was bad news but it
had an advantage which is the rest of
the time that transporter took up more
food the third one the third one the
good thing going for it is that it
didn't have the bad thing was it didn't
have poison the good good thing going
for it was it didn't have to spend
energy on a poison and it didn't have
that transporter so each one of those
has a strength each one of those has a
vulnerability they're like I know
Pokemons or something and you put them
all together there and you get a rock
paper scissors scenario where you get
equilibrium where they are not attacking
each other because note if I am a and I
destroy b b's no longer wiping out C
who's the one who could damage me it's
got to come to an equilibrium state so
you can get the evolution of stalemates
like that and that's quite frequently
seen and note here this was the
evolution of stalemates not in chimps
not in sitations but in bacteria what
we're going to see is
bacterial Behavior to the extent that
this is sort of a metaphor for Behavior
behavior of all sorts of unlikely
species are subject to these same rules
of passing on copies of your genes these
three different strains of bacteria are
competing with each other none of them
are behaving for the good of the species
there of the three of them so rock paper
scissors is very cool and you get
versions of that in humans and that's
been sort of studied quantitatively all
of that but that's not real cooperation
that's merely everybody realizing we
have to cut back on the competition we
have to cut back on the aggression
because every time I damage whoever I am
more vulnerable in another Realm that's
a stalemate that's a truce but you look
at animals and in all sorts of realms
it's not just rock paper scissors
stalemates they're reaching they
actually cooperate with each other. And
you look close enough and you see
they're not relatives. They're not
relatives, yet you get all sorts of
altruistic behavior and you've got it
under a whole bunch of domains because
this brings up the question... why should
you ever be cooperative with another
individual if you're a social animal? At
every possibility, you should stab them
in the back and be selfish. And the
reason why that isn't a good idea is
there's all sorts of circumstances where
many hands make the task light or
whatever that is. Cooperation can have
synergistic benefits. And you see that
with species that are cooperative
hunters where they are not necessarily
relatives they will chase one chasing an
animal while the other is getting ready
to cut a corner on it Cooperative
behavior and they incre the likelihood
of them getting a kill another example
of this researched by a guy named Mark
Hower at Harvard looking at Reese's
monkeys and what he showed was he would
put these monkeys in a situation where
they had access to food they had access
to food under one circumstance where
they could reach for it and take it in
and share it with another monkey under
the other circumstance it required two
monkeys to get the food in there and
what he showed was clear-cut reciprocity
monkeys who were sharing with this guy
were more likely to get shared back with
and got more cooperation when it was a
task where two of them had to work
together to get the food one alone
wasn't enough many hands make the task
lighter under all sorts of circumstances
cooperation has a strong evolutionary
payoff even among
non-relatives with a condition which is
you're not putting more into with then
you are getting that is reciprocal and
this opens up the third building block
of all of this which is reciprocal
altruism cooperation altruistic Behavior
among non-relatives but undergoing very
strict sort of constraints of it's got
to be reciprocated with all sorts of
rules like that so what does that look
like so you're going to see reciprocal
altruism when would you see that what's
the immediate thing what sort of species
would show systems of reciprocal
cooperation among non-relatives they got
to be smart animals they got to be
social they got to be smart why do they
have to be smart because they have to
remember this is the guy who like owes
me a favor from last Thursday they need
to be able to recognize individuals they
have to be long lived enough so that
there's a chance of interacting with
that individual again and establishing
this reciprocity you would thus predict
you would see systems of reciprocal
altruism only in longlived Social
vertebrates but you see the exact sorts
of things in bacteria you see the exact
sort of things in fungi you see that in
all sorts of other Realms you get social
bacteria colonizing bacteria and where
what you might get are two clonal lines
that are together in other words two
genetically two lines Each of which is
all the bacteria have the same genetic
makeup so think of it as one individual
who's just kind of dispersed another one
who's just kind of dispersed and they've
come together in something called a
fruiting body which is how bacteria
reproduce or whatever and there's two
parts to a fruiting body there's one
which is the stock which attaches to
something or other and then there's the
part that actually fruits so you want to
be in the fruiting part because that's
the part that actually reproduces and
the stock is doing all the work there
and what you see is attempts at cheating
attempts at one of these strains trying
to disproportionately wind up in the
Fring part and what you also see is the
next time around this other strain will
not cooperate with it will not form a
social Colony so that's getting played
off at the level of single cell
organisms forming big social colonies
getting played at that level yes as we
will see reciprocal altruism works most
readily in big smart Long Live social
beasts but it can occur in all sorts of
systems so what it's built around is
reciprocal cooperation and intrinsic in
that is another motivation going on
there not just to involve a reciprocal
relationship with a non-relative and
many hands and light tasks and all of
that but also whenever possible to cheat
to take advantage of the other
individual and thus another key facet of
it is to very good at detecting when
somebody is cheating against you to be
vigilant about cheating in what would
otherwise be a stable reciprocal
relationship and an awful lot of social
behavior is built around animals either
trying to get away with something or
spotting somebody else doing the same an
example of it there is a test that's
used in evolutionary psychology where
you're given this very complicated story
or another version of a complicated
story where somebody promises if you do
this you'll get this reward but if you
do that you're going to get this
punishment and like really complex and
in one outcome the outcome of it is the
person isn't supposed to get rewarded
but the individual decides to reward
them spontaneous act of kindness in
another Circumstance the person is the
individual is supposed to get rewarded
and instead they get punished a cheater
in that case and amid these convoluted
stories people are much better 75% to 25
are much better at detecting when
cheating has gone on in the story than
when a random active kindness has gone
on we are more attuned to picking up
cheating and remarkably some very subtle
Studies have been done with chimps
showing that chimps have the same bias
they are much better at picking up
social interactions involving cheating
than ones that involve spontaneous
altruism so you see here this balance
between cooperation and reciprocal and
even among non-relatives and that's
great but you should cheat when you can
get away with it but you should be
vigilant against cheaters and what of
course it comes down to then is tic TCT
toe and giraffe hearts and all of that
what is the optimal strategy in a
particular social species for a
particular individual what is the
optimal strategy when do you cooperate
and when do you cheat when do you defect
on the Cooperative relationship you've
had and this introduces us to a whole
world of mathematics built around what
is called Game Theory the notion that
there are games formal games that have
mathematically optimal strategies or
multiple strategies multi equilibrium
and a whole world of research has been
built around them in terms of when to
cooperate and when to defect so Game
Theory stuff this was starting off in a
world of like people studying economics
and negotiation and diplomacy and all of
that and that was a whole world built
around this logic of when do you
cooperate when do you cheat and what
came out of there were all sorts of
models of how to optimize behavior in
terms of that and the building block
sort of the fruit fly of game theory is
a game called the prisoners
dilemma prisoners dilemma sort of
cutting to Z details two individuals are
prisoners and they escape and they're
both captured and they're interrogated
separately and if both of them refuse to
talk that's great for them if they both
squeal they both get punished if one of
them is able to squeal on the other one
they get a great reward of the other one
what you get formally are four possible
outcomes both individuals
cooperate both individuals cheat against
each other
individual a cooperates and B
cheats individual B cooperates and a
cheats and what you get in prisoners
dilemma is a formal payoff for each what
gives you the greatest payoff stabbing
the other guy in the back you cheat and
they cooperate you have exploited them
you have taken advantage of them isn't
that wonderful that's the highest payoff
in prison or dilemma games second
highest payoff you both
cooperate third third highest payoff
which is beginning to not count as a
payoff but in a lot of the games is set
up as the start of punishment both of
you cheat on each
other fourth worst possible payoff is
you're the sucker you cooperate and the
other individual stabs you in the back
so what the prisoners dilemma game is
set up these circumstances where
individuals will play versions of this
against each other with varying rewards
and that sort of thing and parameters
that we will look at in a lot of detail
and seeing when is it optimal to
cooperate when is it optimal to cheat
when would you do this so you've got
examples of this and this was the
building block and what anyone would say
looking at this is it's obvious what you
want to do is in some way rationally
maximize your payoff this is this whole
world of homo economists the notion of
humans as being purely rational decision
makers and what you begin to see in this
world of game theory is there is
anything but that going on and later in
the course we are going to see something
very interesting people playing
prisoners dilemma games inside a brain
scanner looking at a part of the brain
that has a lot to do with pleasure and
what you see is some individuals
activate that part of the brain when
they've successfully stabbed the other
guy in the back some individuals
activate it when they have both
cooperated and there's a big gender
difference as to which which
circumstance so you just guess which one
is going on there we're going to see a
number of studies like that coming down
the line so the question becomes how do
you optimize prisoner dilic play and
what emerged at that time was the notion
of all sorts of theoretical models and
stuff and then in the 1970s there was an
economist at University of Michigan
named Robert Axelrod who revolutionized
the entire field what he did was he took
some Paleolithic comp computer and
programmed in how the prisoners dilemma
would be played and he could program in
as if they were two players and he could
program in what each one's strategy
would
be and what he then did was he wrote to
all of his buddies and all of his
mathematician friends and prize Fighters
and theologians and serial murderers and
Nobel Peace Prize winners and in each
case explain what was up and saying what
strategy would you use in a prisoner's
dilemma a game and he gets them all back
and he programs all these different
versions and he runs a round robin
tournament every strategy is paired
against every other strategy at one
point or other and you look at what the
payoff is you ask which is the most
optimal strategy and out of it
shockingly to everyone because this was
a computer teaching us optimizing human
behavior out of it came one simple
strategy that always outcompeted the
others this is people sitting there
probabilistic ones as to when to
cooperate and lunar cycles as to what to
do the one that always one is now called
tit
fortat you start off cooperating in the
very first round with the individual you
cooperate if the individual has
cooperated with you in that round you
cooperate in the next round and you
cooperate cooperate as long as the other
individual cooperates but as soon as
there's a round where the individual
cheats against you you cheat against
them the next time if they cheated at
you that time also you cheat against
them the next time if they go back to
cooperating you go back to cooperating
the next time you have this tit fortat
strategy in the absence of somebody
stabbing you in the back you will always
cooperate and what they found was run
these hundreds of thousands of versions
of these round robin tournaments and tit
fortat was the one that was most optimal
to begin to use a word that is not just
going to be a metaphor tit fortat always
drove the other strategies into
Extinction and what you wound up seeing
is this optimized strategy and it was
very clear why tit fortat worked so well
number one it was nice you start off
cooperating number two it retaliates if
you do something crummy to it number
three it is forgiving if you go back to
cooperate
number four it's clearcut in its play
it's not some probabilistic thing and
what you get then with tit fortat is
suppose you're playing three rounds with
another individual you both cooperate
the first one you both cooperate the
next one you're playing tit fortat
strategy so you cooperate on this one
and they stab you in the back and you
can't get back at them because this is
the last round what you'll see is under
lots of circumstances Tit for Tat is
disadvantageous but what the sound bite
is about it is Tit for Tat may lose the
battles but it wins all the wars this
pattern of being nice but being
retaliatory being forgiving and being
clear in the rules drives all the other
strategies into
Extinction okay at this point my alarm
just went off which was to remind me to
ask somebody who is wearing a life vest
is somebody wearing a life
vest over there um where are you
she just left she left isn't that
interesting somebody put me up to having
to ask this person why are you wearing a
life vest and apparently the answer she
would give was going to free all sorts
of captives in some like Rebel group in
Colombia and she fled okay what that
does is
uh I don't know what that says about
reciprocal altruism but what that says
also is after I do a summary don't make
a move we will have a 5 minute break so
what do we have at this point we have a
first building block of optimizing the
evolution of behavior like optimizing
giraffe Hearts first piece you don't
believe behave for the good of the
species individual selection passing on
as many copies of your own genes as
possible sometime a chicken is an egg's
way of making another egg he says
triumphantly building block number two
kin selection some of the time the best
way to pass on copies of your jeans is
by way of helping relatives kin
selection with the mathematical
fierceness of degree of relat is driving
it piece three sometimes what's most
advantageous is to cooperate even with
non-relatives but with the rules of it
has to be reciprocal and you have to
cheat when possible you have to be on
guard against cheaters and as we've just
seen Game Theory prisoners dilemma
beginning to formalize Optimal
strategies for that okay let's take a
five minute
break but promise you will come back if
you go out and everyone won't wander off
of
being maximize that behavior in a very
artificial realm but stay tuned
prisoners dilemma as the building block
of how to do this amid lots of other
types of games that are used but
prisoners dilemma is the most basic one
and that round robin tournament that
computer simulation Axel Rod asking all
his buddies to tell him what strategy
would you use run them against each
other and out comes tit fortat Tit for
Tat Drive all the others into
Extinction however there is a
vulnerability in tit for which
is okay so we have the technical way of
showing prisoners dilemma play and first
round both individuals are cooperating
second round both individuals are
cooperating third round this one cheats
those are fangs this one cheats and this
one cooperates so the next round this
one now cheats and this one goes back to
cooperating and we've just gotten
through a scary thing that Tit for Tat
solves and it's great wonderful what if
though your system is not 100% perfect
what if there's the possibility of a
mistake being made of sending the wrong
signal what if there's the possibility
of noise in the communication system and
at some point an individual who does a
Cooperative Behavior thanks to a glitch
in the system it is read as having been
defect
defection so what happens as a
result this
individual forget it okay what happens
as a result the individual who
cooperated but somehow the message got
through is cheating they don't know
something got lost in the wires between
them in Translation the other individual
was saying whoa that individual cheated
against me I'm going to cheat in the
next round so Along Comes the next round
and that individual cheats against them
this one who's cooperating because
they've been cooperating all along they
don't know about this error and they say
whoa that person just cheated against me
I'm going to cheat in the next round so
they cheat in the next round this one
says Whoa they just cheated another time
again and again and again and what you
get is a seesaw pattern for the rest of
time you've just wiped out 50% of the
cooperation and what you've got is tit
fortat strategies are vulnerable to
Signal error that's something that soon
came out in these studies of axle rods
and when I was a kid there was like one
of these like thriller books I remember
reading where there's a glitch in the
system and at the time the mean scary
Soviet Union launched a missile that no
it was the United States the United
States by accident launched a missile a
nuclear weapon where they didn't mean to
some cockroach you know chewed through a
wire someplace or other and the missile
went off and wound up being destroying
Moscow and oh my God we had a
Cooperative system of mutually sort of
Restraint of aggression all of that and
thanks to a signal error a cheating
signal was accidentally sent off and how
did the book end a tit for response in
order to avoid sort of thermonuclear
Wasteland the Soviet Union was allowed
to destroy New York all right so that
shows exactly how you could then get
into a seawing thing simply by way of if
the system has any vulnerability to
Signal error so it soon became clear as
soon as Axel Rod began to introduce the
possibility of signal errors that tiit
fortat didn't work as well as another
strategy one that quickly came to the
Forefront and that
one for some strange reason that's the
way it's shown that one was called
forgiving tit
fortat what happens with forgiving tit
fortat the usual rule like Tit for Tat
if you cooperate if they cooperate you
always cooperate if they cheat against
you you punish them in the next round
exactly same thing as Tit for Tat but oh
no what if there's a signal error in the
system and you've gotten in one of these
horrible seawing things what forgiving
TI fortat does is we'll have a rule for
example that if we seesaw like this five
times in a row I will foro cheating the
next time and instead I'll cooperate and
that will get things back on track I am
willing to be forgiving in one round in
order to reestablish cooperation after
the signal error came in and that one as
soon as you introduce the Poss
possibility of signal error that one out
competes tit fortat because it makes
perfect sense it's a great way of
solving that
problem so that was terrific tit fortat
but the ability to forgive and what you
would then see is variability how many
of these do you need to go through
before you forgive what's the optimal
number of sees songs all of that so a
whole world of optimizing how soon you
were forgiving nonetheless the general
theme being forgiving TI for Tat out
canach TI for Tat when you can have
signal error but there is a
vulnerability there is a vulnerability
here to this one which is you could be
exploited if you're playing against for
example a tit for tar or all sorts of
other strategies where they don't have
forgiving strings of defection and you
do what's going to happen is you're
going to keep going back to cooperating
and they're going to keep stabbing you
in your back forgiving Tit for Tat is
vulnerable to exploitation playing
against individual players that don't
have forgiveness in them so what soon
became apparent was an even better
strategy which
is you start off with a tit fortat
strategy which is you are punitive you
are retaliatory amid being forgiving
clear nice initially you were willing to
punish and you cannot be exploited in
this way if and only if you have gone
whatever number of rounds without the
other individual ever cheating on you if
you've gone long enough without that
happening you switch over to forgiving
tit fortat what is that that's deciding
you trust somebody you've had enough
interactions with them that you are
willing to trust them this is the
transition from Pure rational optimizing
to switching over forgiveness coming in
there protects you from signal error and
of course now a whole world of how many
rounds do you need to do this before you
switch that as to what the optimal deal
with that is but again this is a way of
transitioning to solve the problem of
signal error but forgiving too readily
and being taken advantage of soon
another strategy appeared which was
called
Pavlov and those of you who know
pavlovian psychology will see that this
in fact has nothing whatsoever to do
with pavlovian psychology and I don't
know why they did that but they thought
it was kind of cool but the rule was
remember if you stab the other guy in
the back you get a bunch of points if
you both cooperate you get points not as
many if you both cheat you lose some
points if you're taken advantage of you
lose a lot of points so two outcomes you
gain two outcomes you lose in Pavo the
simple rule is when I I do something if
I get points if I get some degree of
reward I do it again the next time if I
get rewarded and either of the first two
types of payoffs I do the same thing
again and the other part of course is
and if I have if I play my strategy and
I lose one of the two bottom the two
bottom outcomes I switch to the other
strategy the next time and what you see
is that can establish very good Tit for
Tat stuff but if you sit and spend hours
tonight with you know a long roll of
toilet paper and playing out all the
rounds of it you will see what pav love
allows you to do is exploit somebody
else who is forgiving so Pavlov goes
along just fine with this and as long as
Pavlov continues whenever they switch
over to a forgiving tit fortat Pavlov
will outcompete them because Pavlov
exploits what then emerged was just
zillions of people stud all sorts of
games like this and there's other ones
ultimatum game is a trust game where
it's the same notion of business there
which is you choose to cooperate you
choose to cheat what's the optimal
outcome there are mathematically optimal
outcomes that you can use and you run
all of it against the computer and you
get the optimization popping out the
other end wonderful so there's Axel rod
and there's buddies using terms like oh
this strategy will drive the other one
into Extinction or this strategy works
but if you program in that every now and
then there could be a glitch there can
be a mutation this will be they're using
all this biology jargon obviously
metaphorically but right around this
point the biologists look at this who
are just beginning to think about the
social biology stuff formal patterns of
optimizing behavior and they say whoa
does this apply to the behavior of real
organisms because at this point it's
just economists and computer types and
diplomats learning when to optimize all
that sort of thing around the time there
was a paper published somewhat before
that this is a name nobody is going to
know lost in history a guy named Daniel
Ellsberg Daniel Ellsberg became very
famous around 1970 by he was working in
the Pentagon and he stole thousands of
pages of secret files there and gave it
to the New York Times showing how utter
corrupt everything that went on behind
the scenes was and getting us into
Vietnam major blow out all of that he
had spent the early part of his career
perfectly happily working in the
Pentagon for the military as a game
theorist as a game theorist coming up
with optimal patterns and he wrote one
paper called the optimal benefits of
perceived
Madness what what times do you want your
opponent to think you were absolutely
out of your mind and good to do all
sorts of crazy stuff and where they wind
up cooperating to keep you from doing
that the advantages of Madness what's
that that systems where things like
mutually assured destruction doesn't
work because you're willing to set it
off that the advantages of Madness this
whole world of people working on it
mathematicians and more strategists and
there's the zoologists now looking at
this saying whoa this is cool I wonder
if animals behave that way and that's
when people now armed with their
insights into prisoners dilemma and tit
fortat and all this stuff started to go
and study animals out in the wild and
see were there any examples where this
happened yes in all sorts of interesting
Realms first example vampire bats
vampire bats we are all set up to be
creeped out by vampire bats but in
actuality when you see a vampire bat
drinking the blood of some cow or
something you are watching at a mommy
getting food for her babies because
vampire bat mothers are not actually
drinking the blood they're filling up
this throat sack thing and they go back
to the nest and they discourage the
blood to feed their babies she's just
watching out for her kids it happens
that vampire bats have an interesting
system of reciprocal altruism which is a
whole bunch of females will share the
same nest we'll have all their kids in
there mixed in and these are not
necessarily related so so we've just
left the world of kin selection they're
not necessarily related but they have
reciprocal altruist system each female
comes in Discord disgorges the blood and
feeds everybody's babies and they'll all
feed each other's babies and everything
is terrific and they have this blood
vampire commune going there and they
have reached a nice state of stable
cooperation now make the bats think that
one of the females is cheating on them
out comes that female flying off to find
some blood and instead you net her and
get a hold of her and take some syringe
full of air and pump up the throat sack
so the throat sack is really full and
distended but there's no blood in there
you just pumped air into there and stick
her back into the nest there and she's
just sitting there happily and the other
females are sitting saying look at her
look at how much blood she's got there I
can't believe it cuz she's not feeding
our kids she's cheating on us and the
next time they go out to feed the other
females don't feed her kids a Tit for
Tat and what you saw here is an exact
example of introducing signal error
signal error in this case being some
grad student pumping up the throat of
some vampire bat and showing that
they're using a version of a Tit for Tat
strategy totally amazing people were
blown away by this another example fish
stickleback fish who in the world of
animals you know bats are probably not
some of the brightest folks around but I
don't think sticklebacks are within
light years of them but stickleback fish
can do a tid fortat strategy here's what
you do you have a stickleback fish in
your in your fish tank and you make the
fish you make him believe that he's
being attacked by another fish what do
you do you put a mirror up against the
edge of the tank there so within a very
short time I told you they were not that
smart so but in a very short time he's
lunging forward at this mirrored thing
and maintaining his territory against
this guy and barely holding on and that
other guy is just he doesn't get tired
thank God I don't get tired and they're
just going at it and now make him think
he has a Cooperative partner put in a
second mirror that's perpendicular here
in other words he sees his reflection
there and every time he moves forward he
sees that one moving forward and which
is fortunate because he's also seeing
another fish coming from that way and
he's sitting there saying this is great
I don't know who this guy is but wow
what a team we are doubles this is great
he's in there in the thick it's funny
how those two guys are so synchronized
but whoa we're holding them off and
we're doing now make him think his
cooperating partner is in fact cheating
on him take the mirror and angle it back
a little bit so the reflection is set
back some and what he now sees is the
fish moving forward but not all the way
up to the wall there the fish is hanging
back back there the fish is cheating and
this stickle back is sitting there
saying in effect that son of a I
can't believe he's doing that to me
we've worked together for years I can't
believe he's oh he's pretending to go
forward but I see he's not really doing
that fortunately that guy isn't coming
forward anymore either pH but I can't
believe that guy's cheating and the next
time you set up this scenario the next
time move the chance the stickle back
doesn't attack its own reflection there
it is tit for tatting against this guy
so here we've managed to set up one of
these deals within one fish and carrying
it out forever one fish ultimately with
some very blistered lips Tit for Tat
once again another example this is the
most bizarre one I can imagine and leads
to all sorts of subjects that are going
to come many lectures from now but there
are fish species that will change sex
and they do it under all sorts of
strategic circumstances that suddenly
begin to fit into this realm of what
we've been learning about out and you've
got one of these things called black
Hamlet fish and they can change gender
so you'll have a pair of them who hang
out with each other of opposite genders
and they take turns they flip back and
forth for a while this one's female and
for a while this one's female and they
go back and forth and that's great but
there's an inequity there which is that
the price of reproduction is greater for
the female than for the male as is the
case in so many species the female is
doing all that egg and over duct and
progesterone stuff or whatever it is and
the males just got to come up with some
sperm there doing reproduction as a
cooperating pair they're not relatives
reciprocal altruism maximizing each of
their reproductions whoever is the
female in any given round is the one
who's paying more and what you see are
reciprocal relationships there of the
fish using Tit for Tat if you get one
fish that begins to cheat and winds up
being a male too much the time the other
fish stops cooperating with them again
tit fortat stuff so people were just
blown out of the water at this point
seeing whoa forget rational human
economic thinking and all of that you go
out into the wild and bats and
stickleback fish and gender switching
fish and all of that they're following
some of the exact same strategies isn't
nature amazing no nature isn't amazing
it's the exact same logic as saying a
giraffe has to have heart that's strong
enough to pump blood to the top of the
head of a giraffe or else there wouldn't
be giraffe and when you look at this
realm it's applying the same notion the
same sort of wind tunnel of selective
optimization for behavior in this case
went to cheat went to cooperate sculpt
something that is as optimized as a
giraffe's heart being the right size so
this made perfect sense wonderful but
then people began to look a little bit
closer and began to see sort of the very
distressing real world beginning to
creep in there which were exceptions
first exception this was done by a guy
named Craig Packer University of
Minnesota looking at lions in East
Africa and what you get is typically
Prides are a whole bunch of relatives
usually females sisters nieces all of
that but you will sometimes get Prides
that are not of close relatives
nonetheless they will get you know
reciprocal altruistic things going on
lions in this case having the same trick
as was done on those vervet monkeys
researcher putting inside the bush there
a speaker and playing the sound of like
400 menacing Lions all at once and you
know what you're supposed to do is freak
out at that point and all of you need to
very carefully approach and see what's
going on in that bush so what would
happen in a reciprocal system and
everybody do this does this or if one
time one of them cheats on you you push
that one forward the next time time or
some such thing that's what you would
expect but what he would begin to notice
is in a bunch of these groups there'd be
one scaredy cat lion one who habitually
stayed behind the others and who wasn't
punished for it so this produced this
first puzzle that oh sometimes animals
aren't optimizing tit fortat sometimes
animals haven't read Robert axelrod's
Landmark 1972 paper that sort of thing
and what you suddenly have is the real
world what could be possible
explanations one thing being maybe
they're not really paying attention
maybe they're not quite that smart wait
bacteria are doing versions of tit
fortat what else could be going on oh
Lions interact in other Realms maybe
this individual is doing very reciprocal
stuff forgiving overly altruistic stuff
in some other realm of behavior maybe
this lion is eats less of the meat and
backs off earlier or something like that
maybe there's another game going on
simultaneously and this introducing the
real world in which it is not just two
individuals sitting there playing
prisoners dilemma and optimizing you
suddenly begin to get real world
complexities coming in there and by the
time we get to the lectures way down the
line on aggression and cooperation what
you will see is things get really
complicated when you have individuals
playing games simultaneously the rules
that you apply to Oney logically begin
to dribble into the other one all sorts
of things like that it will get very
complicated so first hint there that in
fact everything doesn't work perfectly
along those lines here's another version
here's one of the truly weird species
out there something called the naked
mole rat if you ever have nothing to do
and you've got Google image up there go
like spend the evening looking up
closeup pictures of naked mole rats
these are like the weirdest things out
there they are the closest things among
the mammals to social insects in terms
of how their colonies work they're
totally bizarre all of that but they
live in these big Cooperative colonies
that are predominantly underground in
Africa and they were discovered I think
only in the 1970s or so and for a while
when zoologists got together if you were
a naked mole rat person you were just
the coolest around and everybody else
would feel intimidated cuz you were
working on the best species out there
and you would see these big Cooperative
colonies soon shown to not necessarily
be of relatives and reciprocity all
those sorts of rules but people soon
began to recognize there would be one or
two animals in each colony that weren't
doing any work work digging out
tunnels bookkeeping I don't know what
naked mole rats do in terms of work but
there would be a few individuals who
would just be sitting around and there
was these big old naked mole rats they
were much bigger than the other ones and
were scarfing up food left and right
there goes Robert Axel rod down the
drain there goes all that optimization
because no one would be punishing these
guys what's the deal and it took enough
watching these animals long enough to
see this notion of oh there's another
game going on in which they play a more
important role and it is sort of
dribbling across when the rainy season
comes these big naked mole rats go up
and turn around and they plug the entry
to the tunnels there that's what they do
and suddenly these guys who have been
sitting around doing no work whatsoever
all year and eating tons of stuff they
suddenly have to now stick their rear
ends out for the coyotes to be around or
whatever it is that predates them what
we have is role diversification real
animals real organisms are not just
playing one formal prisoners dilemma
game against each other at the same time
and by the time we again get to the
later lectures on aggression cooperation
all of that we will not only see the
things get much more complicated when
you're playing simultaneous games when
you're playing a game against one
individual while you're playing against
another one and them against triangular
circumstances how play differs if you
know how many rounds you were playing
against the individual versus if you
have no idea how play differs if when
you were about to play against someone
you get to find out what their behavior
has been in the previous trials with
other individuals in other words if
somebody shows up with a reputation
we'll see this is a much more
complicated world of playing out these
games a much more realistic one so we
begin to see a first pass at all this
optimization stuff and how great that
all is one final interesting addition to
this game theory world of thinking about
Behavior like that which came from a guy
named James Holland who
apparently might have a different first
name but Holland apparently is an
interesting piece recent history he's
the P first person to ever get a PhD in
Computer Sciences which I think was in
the late 50s University of Michigan
apparently there are Realms of of
computer programmers who worship this
guy and he like a lot of other folks in
that business got interested in this
game theory evolution of optimal
strategies and he designed ways of
running all of this and he introduced a
new Ripple which is the possibility of a
strategy suddenly changing the
possibility of a mutation
and what he could then study was
mutations how often they were adaptive
how often they spread throughout the
strategy there of individuals playing
how often they drove the other
strategies into Extinction versus ones
that were quickly driven to Extinction
themselves more cases where we are
getting these systems where maybe
they're not just metaphorically using
terms from biology maybe they are
exactly modeling the same thing and we
will see more and more evidence for that
okay so reciprocal altruism how would
that play out in the world of natural
selection natural selection Cooperative
hunting and there's lots of species that
have Cooperative hunting wild dogs
Jackal some other species as well that's
clearly that's like the definition of
Cooperative hunting of Cooperative
reciprocal altruism if they're not
relatives how would sexual selection
play out in the realm of reciprocal
altruism a little bit less obvious there
that would be if you and some
non-relative spend an insane amount of
energy and time making sure you both
look really good before going to the
prom that would be sexual selection
working on reciprocal altruistic system
so what we have now are our three
building blocks this whole trashing of
it's not survival of the fittest it's
not behaving for the good of the species
it's not behaving for the good of the
group but instead these three building
blocks the ways to optimize as many
copies of your genes in the next
generation is possible way number one
individual selection a version of
selfish jeans sometimes a chicken is an
egg way of making another egg behavior
is just the way of getting copies of
genes into the Next Generation piece
number two Inclusive fitness kin
selection that whole business that's
Sometimes the best way of passing on
copies is to help relatives do it and
it's as a function of how related there
the whole world of cooperation more
among related organisms than unrelated
ones and as we will see way down the
line what is very challenging in
different species is how do you figure
out who you're related to and humans do
it in a very unique way that sets them
up for being exploited in all sorts of
circumstances that begin to explain why
culture after culture people are really
not nice to thems and it flows along
those lines this is something we will
get to in a lot of detail so degree of
relatedness a lecture coming how do you
tell who who you're related to but that
second piece kin selection third piece
reciprocal altruism you scratch my back
and I'll scratch your back and whenever
possible you want to instead scratch
your back and they want to make sure
you're not scratching your back or
whatever cheating counts as but trying
to cheat being vigilant against it
formal games where you can optimize it
very complicated and can you believe it
you go out into the real world and you
find examples of precisely that
optimization with Tit for Tat is nature
wonderful it's got to work that way and
then you begin to see how the real world
is more complicated multiple roles naked
mole rats stuck in plumbing things of
that sort okay so these are the
principles and what people of the school
of evolutionary thought would say armed
with these sorts of principles you could
now look at all sorts of interesting
domains of animal behavior and
understand what the behavior is going to
be like by using these okay we start
with the first example
here we return to these guys and we have
one species here and knowing this guy
had a penis and this one nursed we've
got an adult male an adult female what
is it that you can conclude in this
species males are a lot bigger than
females so let's state it here as
there's a big ratio of males to females
meanwhile in the next County you've
discovered another species where
somebody's got a penis and somebody else
is nursing and their skulls are the
exact same size oh here's a species
where there's no difference in body size
between males and females okay so let's
begin to see just using the principles
we've got in hand already what sort of
stuff we can
predict starting okay which of those
species in one case you have males being
a lot bigger than females in one case
you've got males being the same size as
females and which of those species the
first one like this or the same siiz
ones and which ones would you expect to
see more male
aggression first one okay how
come their bodies are built for it which
begins to tell you something their
bodies are built for it maybe because
females have been selecting for that you
will see higher levels of aggression in
species like this where there's a big
body size difference and much less of it
in these guys next you now ask how much
variability is there in male productive
success in one of these species all the
males have one or two kids over their
lifetime in another species 95% of the
reproducing is carried out by 5% of the
males a huge variability skew in male
reproductive success which species do
you get the every male has a couple of
kids and that's about it and all equally
so which
one second one how come
because these guys are being selected
for aggression if they're fighting there
is going to have to be something they're
fighting for differential reproductive
access okay so you see more
variability in species that look like
this next females come into the equation
what do females want what do females
want in the species on the left versus
the one on the right the one on the
right you know again skull the same size
same body size on the left what does the
female
want what sort of male is the female
interested in big exactly that's exactly
the driving force on this how come
because she's not going to get anything
else out of this guy this guy is just
going to like the Pres is going to be
some sperm it might as well be some good
sperm some genetically well-endowed
sperm that makes for a big healthy
Offspring increasing the odds of her
passing on copies of her genes in the
Next Generation what about in this
species what's females looking
for okay good hold on to that for a
second and let's Jump Ahead a few lines
one of the species males have never been
known to do the slightest affiliative
thing with infants they just get
irritated and harass them and all of
that and the other you have soccer dads
who are doing as much raising of the
kids as the females are in which species
do you get lots of male parental
Behavior the one on the right okay so
lots of male parental Behavior
here so somebody just gave the answer
here female Choice what would you see in
this species you want big muscular guys
you want whatever is selling that season
for what counts as a hot male because
you want your Offspring to have those
traits and somebody else called out here
what do females want in this category
and what was it you said good
personality good personality yes able to
express
emotions that
too okay somebody else shouted out
something that gets at the broader more
globally Oprah version okay somebody
shouted out P parental Behavior you want
a male who is going to be competent at
raising your children what is it that
you want really most deeply you want to
get the male who is the most like a
female you can get a hold of you don't
want some big old stupid guy with a lot
of muscle and canines who's wasting
energy on stuff like that that he could
be using instead on you know reading
good night moon or some such thing what
you want instead is somebody who's as
close to a female as you can get to
without getting this lactation stuff
males are chosen who are the same size
as females so the term given here is you
know choosing for paternal Behavior
parental Behavior parental let's just
put that in there and that begins to
explain the Top Line species in which
there's a lot of sexual dimorphism
morphism Shapes of Things sexual
dimorphism big difference in body size
as a function of gender and in these
sorts of species where you get male Al
Behavior not much variability male
reproductive success low levels of
aggression and what females want is a
competent male these are ones where you
see low degrees of sexual dimorphism so
how's a female going to figure out that
this guy is going to be a competent
parent you know once again we just
figured out if he looks kind of like you
because that suggests he hasn't wasted
health and Metabolism on stupid
pointless muscles when there's more
important things in life for making sure
your kids have good values what else
would the female want to know when she's
first considering mating with the
male is he a nice guy is he sensitive
does he Express his feelings is he
competent at being a parent what do you
want the individual to do prove to you
that he can provide for the kids and
suddenly you have a world of bird male
birds courting the females by bringing
them worms bringing them evidence that
they are able to successfully forage
they are able to get food female choices
built around
appearance and behavioral competence at
being able to be a successful parent in
order to pass on as many copies of genes
the Next Generation as possible okay how
about
lifespan in which species is there a big
difference and life expectancy is a
function of
gender first one here are you choosing
for males to be as close to females as
possible andless the physiology here you
got these guys who are like using huge
amounts of energy to build up all this
muscle which takes a lot more work to
keep in calories and you're more
vulnerable in famines you've got these
males with high testosterone which does
bad stuff to your circulatory system
you've got males who thanks to all this
aggression are getting more injuries
more likely in species in which you have
a lot of sexual dimorphism in body size
you get a lot of sexual dimorphism in
lifespan and then you look at these guys
and it's basically no difference by
gender moving on considering primates
that are of one of these two patterns in
which one do you always want to give
birth to twins in which one do you never
want to give birth to twins who gives
birth to
twins the one on the right of course how
come because you got two parents on the
scene you are not a single mother and
you are a single mother rees's monkey or
something and you give birth to twins
and you do not have the remotest chance
of enough energy enough calories on
board to get both of them to survive a
twin that is born in a species like this
has the same rate that it occurs in
humans about a 1% rate and it is almost
inevitable that one of them does not
survive meanwhile there's a whole world
of primate species with this profile
where the females always
twin finally you are the female and you
are con contemplating bailing out on
your kids and disappearing because
there's some really hot guy over there
who you want to mate with
and you are trying to figure out this
strategy so you are going to leave and
abandon your kids in which species do
you see that
behavior the one on the right the one on
the right because you bail out and the
male is there taking care of them you
bail out in here and you've lost your
investment and copies of your genes for
the Next Generation you see female
cuckoldry this great Victorian term you
see females cheating on the fathers in
this species but not in species like
this because the father is long gone in
you know three other counties there
according somebody else and doesn't
matter you're not going to get any help
from him in primate species of this
profile you always see twinning and they
both survive and what Studies have shown
in these species and we'll get to them
shortly is after birth in fact the males
are expending more calories taking care
of The Offspring than the females go
bail out on him and go find some other
hot guy which in your species counts as
some guy who looks even more like you
than he does in terms of what you want
out of the individual so that so what
have we done here we've just gone
through applying these principles in
this logical way and everybody from the
very first step was getting the right
outcome and go and these are exactly the
profiles you find in certain species
among social mammals these would be
referred to as a tornament species a
tornament species whereas the one on the
right is referred to as a pair bonding a
monogamous species because in this one
males and females stay together because
they both have equivalent investment in
taking care of the kids all of that what
you have here is this contrast between
tornament species and pair bonding
species tornament species these are all
the species where you get males with big
bright plumage these are peacocks these
are all those bird and fish species
where the males are all brightly colored
what are the females choosing for
peacock feathers does not make for a
good peacock mother peacock feathers are
signs of being healthy enough that you
can waste lots of energy on these big
stupid pointless feathers that's a sign
of Health that's a sign of all I'm
getting from this peacock as jeans I
might as well go for good ones that's
the world of peacocks that's the world
of chickens with pecking orders
dominating like that lots of aggression
that's the world of primates where as in
Savannah baboons the male is twice as
big as the female tornament species
where a lot of passing on of genes is
decided by male male aggression in the
context of tournaments producing massive
amounts of
variability in reproductive success
where males are being selected for being
good like this so they sure being
selected for having big bodies which
winds up meaning a shortened lifespan
for a bunch of reasons females are
choosing for that these are guys who are
not using their energy on Parental
Behavior thus you do not want to have
twins if you were a female baboon and
you do not want to bail out on the kids
because nobody else is going to take
care of them go and look at a new
primate species and see this much of a
difference in skull size and you've just
be able to derive everything else about
its social behavior meanwhile these guys
on the right peir bonding species these
are found among South American monkeys
Mar missets tamarinds you put up a
picture of them which I will do if I
ever Master PowerPoint in some
subsequent lecture you put up a picture
of a maret pair and you can't tell who's
the male and the female this is not the
world of mandrel baboons with males with
big bright bizarre coloration on the
face and with antlers when the females
don't and that whole world of sexual
dimorphism you can't tell which one is
the male and which one is the female
maret by looking at them you can't tell
by seeing how long they live you can't
tell by how much they're taking care of
the kids you can't tell in terms of
their reproductive variability that's a
whole different world of selection all
of the South American Tamarind and
marmosets the females always twin they
have a higher rate of aldry of
abandoning the kids the males take as
much care if not more of the kids than
the female does very low levels of
aggression same body size same lifespan
all the males have low degree of
variability how come because if you're
some maret male you don't want to get 47
maret females pregnant because you are
going to have to take care of all the
kids because as we will see way down on
the line in lectures on Parental
Behavior the wiring there as such as
bonding with The Offspring and taking
care of them no wonder among species
like these you have very low variability
all the males reproduce once or twice
this is the world of 5% of the guys
accounting for 95% of the matings this
is totally remarkable because again that
starting point you start off here and
you look at these and oh you can tell if
they were bipedal and or they diseased
and Mal nourish simply by a applying
these principles of individual selection
reciprocity all of that one factoid you
see a new primate species and you see
one nursing and one with a penis and
they're the same size or there is
different to the size and you already
know all about their social system very
consistent across Birds
across fish across primates of all of
those this dichotomy between tornament
species and parab bonding species as we
will see way down the line among some
species types of vs rodents that are
famous in Hallmark cards for their pair
bonding for their monogamy so we'll see
they're not quite as monogamous as you
would think but nonetheless a general
structure like
this so one asks expectedly where do
humans fit in on this one where do
humans fit and the answer is
complicatedly are we a tornament species
are we a parab bonding species what's up
with that
what we will see is we're kind of in
between when you look at the degree of
sexual dimorphism we are not like
baboons but we're sure not like
marmosets we're somewhere in the middle
variability is somewhere in the middle
there I'm not going near that one
lifespan the dimorphism and lifespan
tends to be in between and parental
behavior and likelihood all of those you
look at a number of measures and by next
lecture we will be looking at some
genetics of what monogamous species and
tornament species look like and we're
right in the middle in other words that
explains like 90% of literature because
we're not a classic tornament species
and we're not a classic parab bonding
one we are terribly confused in the
middle there and everything about
anthropology supports that most people
on the planet right now are in a form of
monogamous relationships in a culture
that allows that demands
monogamy an awful lot of people who are
in monogamous relationships in such
cultures aren't really monogamous
relationships traditionally most
cultures on this planet allowed polygamy
nonetheless in most of those polygamous
cultures the majority of individuals
were parab bonded and monogamous you get
two different versions of polygamy in
different social systems of humans one
is economic polygamy which is your
basically sitting around and the
wealthiest guy in the village is the one
who can have the largest number of wives
an enormous skew and reproductive
success that's driven by economics the
other type is demographic you have a
culture where for example you have a
warrior class guys spent 10 years as
Warriors Warriors Warriors New York City
accent as Warriors they don't worry
there's no anxiety but they eventually
worry about getting a wife because by
the time they're done being a warrior
they're like 25
and they marry someone who's 13 which is
what you see in a lot of traditional
cultures that follow that pattern and at
that point you got a problem which is an
awful lot of those guys have been killed
over the course of 10 years of being
involved in high levels of aggression
and 10 more years of life expectancy to
catch up with you there's a shortage of
males so you see polygamy there driven
by demographics and you see polygamy
driven by economics and other types of
society so most cultures on the this
planet allow traditionally before the
missionaries got them most cultures on
this planet allow polygamy nonetheless
within most polygamous cultures the
majority of people are not polygamous we
have one really confused screwed up
Species here because we are halfway in
between in all sorts of these measures
okay so what do we have next which we
will pick up on on Friday what we've
just started with here is the first case
of using all these principles individual
selection kin selection reciprocal
altruism to understand all sorts of
aspects of behavior we will then move on
to seeing how they explain other aspects
of animal behavior some ones which if
you are behaving for the good of the
species circa 1960 there's no
explanation at all because you're doing
things like killing other members of
your species and then finally we will
see how this applies to humans and some
of the witheringly
appropriate for more please visit us at
stanford.edu